<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rails | jjasghar rants and ramblings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-08T11:13:31-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[JJ Asghar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to add growl notifications to rspec tests]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2014/04/08/how-to-add-growl-notifications-to-rspec-tests/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-08T10:45:59-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2014/04/08/how-to-add-growl-notifications-to-rspec-tests</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With some pushing from my work I&rsquo;ve decided to start learning rails, with rails comes TDD.
I&rsquo;m reading some books and watching some screencasts, and rspec testing came up as the default testing way.  I&rsquo;m a
huge <a href="http://kitchen.ci">test-kitchen</a>, or <a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/bats">bats</a> or the like tester with chef
but never got a way to automate the testing in the background. Turns out using rspec+guard+growl allows for you to
be focused on your present screen and have the tests being run with a pop up.</p>

<p>I use vim as my development platform. This is why I needed a way to run rspec in the background, hopping out of the vim buffer breaks my focus. So I used guard-rspec, it was perfect for what I wanted to do, problem was it was in another tab or terminal again breaking my focus. I figured I have growl installed, so this is how I set up this perfect rspec+guard+growl setup.</p>

<p>First add these two gems to your Gemfile:
```ruby
group :development, :test do</p>

<pre><code>gem ...
gem 'growl'
gem 'growl_notify'
</code></pre>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>NOTE: I suggest adding this to the development/test group, you won&rsquo;t want this in your production deploy.</p>

<p>Go ahead and run <code>bundle</code>.</p>

<p>After that, you need to install something called <a href="http://growl.cachefly.net/GrowlNotify-2.1.zip">GrowlNotify 2.1</a>, I&rsquo;d double check your growl version, it only works with 2.1.x.</p>

<p>After installing spin up <code>guard</code>, and you should see a nice notification. :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
