<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: chef | jjasghar rants and ramblings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/categories/chef/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-07T10:45:15-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[JJ Asghar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to fix https://chef defaulting running chef client on open source chef server]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/05/how-to-fix-https-slash-slash-chef-defaulting-running-chef-client-on-open-source-chef-server/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-05T16:59:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/05/how-to-fix-https-slash-slash-chef-defaulting-running-chef-client-on-open-source-chef-server</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I went to #chef on freenode and maek helped me out.  Here’s a run down of how to fix it. Alas the gists are gone; sorry. :(</p>

<p>If you play with open source chef you might run into this.</p>

<p><code>
18:42 j^2 so i’m having trouble with chef-client
18:42 j^2 why does it default to https://chef/blahblah?
18:43 j^2 example:
18:43 j^2 https://gist.github.com/jjasghar/5873e421a7f8365194e3
18:44 j^2 any advice?
18:44 j^2 i guess i could add it to /etc/hosts, but i’d like it to use the chef_server_url is that the point of it?
18:45 maek j^2:  I just got hit with this also
18:45 maek i think becuase chef 11 is now fronted with nginx
18:45 maek its doing a rewrite
18:45 maek for the name configured in nginx
18:45 maek in this case its hostname
18:45 maek but i assume that box cant resolve chef
18:46 j^2 lame
18:46 maek j^2:  I had to end up adding a hosts entry
18:46 maek while I wait for dns
18:46 maek I think you could do
18:46 j^2 yeah that seems like the only option but it’s stuff dumb :(
18:47 maek you could reconfigure chef
18:47 maek to use its ip
18:47 maek instead of its hostname
18:47 j^2 tried the ip in chef_server_url didnt work either; wait you mean nginx?
18:48 @ssd7 maek: Re your question above. I believe you should be able to edit bookshelf[‘vip’] in your config and the run a reconfigure
18:48 maek i dont see it htought
18:48 j^2 oh!
18:48 maek default[‘chef_server’][‘bookshelf’][‘vip’] = node[‘fqdn’]
18:48 j^2 nice looking
18:48 maek yeah
18:48 maek there it is
</code></p>

<p>Or you can do this also, I believe this is how I fixed it myself.:</p>

<p><code>
18:48 maek so you can do
18:49 maek in /etc/chef-server/chef-server.rb
18:49 maek bookshelf[‘vip’] = ‘192.168.1.1’
18:50 j^2 yeah i dont thave that file. :(
18:50 maek and run chef-server-ctl reconfigure
18:50 j^2 ah cool
18:50 maek its for overrides
18:50 maek just make it
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving from one chef to multiple chefs]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/04/moving-from-one-chef-to-multiple-chefs/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-04T14:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/04/moving-from-one-chef-to-multiple-chefs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s a organic growth of a Ops team using chef goes through.  You start out with a <code>chef_repo</code> then you post it to github/some DVCS.  From there you tell people to clone it down and put PRs against it. From there you attempt to be a gate keeper, looking at the commits in the log, realizing that there is no match ups. From there you say to yourself &ldquo;Hey, ok, these guys are pretty smart, as long as I spot check, they should be able to merge things in and I can trust them right?&rdquo; NO you are lying to yourself you just don&rsquo;t realize it yet.</p>

<p>Wait for that one day that you think you have the newest cookbook and you bump the version, add your changes and you upload, and push&hellip;and nothing happens. Oh I&rsquo;m 2x behind where I thought great, bump and push. Oh&hellip;it seems there was a critical fix in that one that I didnt get for that exact cookbook I uploaded&hellip;crap. (And other situations like this can pop up.)</p>

<p>So, I pinged <a href="https://twitter.com/nathenharvey">Nathen Harvey</a> at Opscode asking for some guidance, he suggested <a href="https://github.com/jonlives/knife-spork">knife-spork</a>.  So far with my initial tests it looks like it is the correct answer,  so I&rsquo;m also writing this as a HOWTO for my company so this is just a run down of how to use it. (A cheatsheet to the README.md if you will.)</p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>Obviously the first thing you need to do is install it. Luckily it&rsquo;s a gem so you can just do the following. If you read the docs there are a bunch of places that you <code>.yml</code> gets read from, but I chose this because I like having all my chef stuff in <code>.chef</code> so I don&rsquo;t have to think about pulling anything other than <code>.chef</code> if I want to move boxes.</p>

<p><code>bash
gem install knife-spork
touch ~/.chef/spork-config.yml
</code></p>

<p>After installing the gem and touching the file, you can run <code>knife spork info</code>, it should say everything is disabled.  If so, then you are read to create the config file.</p>

<p>The example <a href="https://raw.github.com/jonlives/knife-spork/master/README.md">config</a> is on the main site, but I copied the demo one here too.</p>

<p>```yaml
default_environments:
  &ndash; development
  &ndash; production
environment_groups:
  qa_group:</p>

<pre><code>- quality_assurance
- staging
</code></pre>

<p>  test_group:</p>

<pre><code>- user_testing
- acceptance_testing
</code></pre>

<p>version_change_threshold: 2
environment_path: &ldquo;/home/me/environments&rdquo;
plugins:
  campfire:</p>

<pre><code>account: myaccount
token: a1b2c3d4...
</code></pre>

<p>  hipchat:</p>

<pre><code>api_token: ABC123
rooms:
  - General
  - Web Operations
notify: true
color: yellow
</code></pre>

<p>  jabber:</p>

<pre><code>username: YOURUSER
password: YOURPASSWORD
nickname: Chef Bot
server_name: your.jabberserver.com
server_port: 5222
rooms:
  - engineering@your.conference.com/spork
  - systems@your.conference.com/spork
</code></pre>

<p>  git:</p>

<pre><code>enabled: true
</code></pre>

<p>  irccat:</p>

<pre><code>server: irccat.mydomain.com
port: 12345
gist: "/usr/bin/gist"
channel: ["chef-annoucements"]
</code></pre>

<p>  graphite:</p>

<pre><code>server: graphite.mydomain.com
port: 2003
</code></pre>

<p>  eventinator:</p>

<pre><code>url: http://eventinator.mydomain.com/events/oneshot
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>All in all this seems pretty self <a href="https://github.com/jonlives/knife-spork#default-environments">explanatory</a> but the most important things to change are <code>environment_path</code> and disabling the plugins (by removing them) here.  For my company I only used the git plugin and&hellip;well that was it. :)</p>

<p>By the way there are only a few plugins, <a href="https://github.com/jonlives/knife-spork/tree/master/plugins">here</a> is a link to the different .md files on each.</p>

<p>Ok, so you have everything set up, what do you do now?</p>

<h2>Usage</h2>

<p>The first step is to run <code>knife spork check COOKBOOK --all</code> where COOKBOOK is one of your commonly updated/tweaked cookbooks.  Spork checks against what you have locally compared to what&rsquo;s in the server, like this:</p>

<p><code>
knife spork check COOKBOOK --all
</code></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example:
```bash
Checking versions for cookbook nagios&hellip;</p>

<p>Local Version:
  5.1.5</p>

<p>Remote Versions: (* indicates frozen)
  5.1.5
  5.1.4
  5.1.3
  5.1.2</p>

<p>ERROR: The version 5.1.5 exists on the server and is not frozen. Uploading will overwrite!
```</p>

<p>As you can see with the error, it&rsquo;s pretty self explaintory.</p>

<p>The second step is to bump the version:
<code>bash
knife spork bump nagios patch
Git: Pulling latest changes from /Users/jasghar/repo/chef_repo/environments
Pulling latest changes from git submodules (if any)
Git: Pulling latest changes from /Users/jasghar/repo/chef_repo/cookbooks/nagios
Pulling latest changes from git submodules (if any)
Successfully bumped nagios to v5.1.6!
</code></p>

<p>Now as you can see I have the git plugin working, and it without thinking about it, updates the metadata.rb so you don&rsquo;t have to. (I HATE that part of chef, I always forget.) Now you can go off make your changes.</p>

<p>From here you&rsquo;re happy, you&rsquo;ve commited your new <code>chef_repo</code> back to the DVCS that you use.  This is where the magic happens: <code>knife spork upload COOKBOOK</code>.  This thing is great, it (to quote the <code>README.md</code>) <em>This function works mostly the same as normal knife cookbook upload COOKBOOK except that this automatically freezes cookbooks when you upload them.</em> Which is the bread and butter of spork.  The freezing is crazy important, by freezing the upload you take &ldquo;ownership&rdquo; of that version of the cookbook.  Your changes are yours, and no-one can mess with them.  So in turn you don&rsquo;t step on your coworkers toes and he doesen&rsquo;t step on yours.</p>

<p>Ok, so this was the cheatsheet, we have implymented this at my company now, so hopefully this goes great. If not&hellip;well that&rsquo;s a different conversation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adventures with chef-solo]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/08/02/adventures-with-chef-solo/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T14:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/08/02/adventures-with-chef-solo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started my chef career with inheriting a chef infrastructure with an opensource chef server.  I read all of the blog posts, and the tutorials, tried to wrap my head around what a cookbook, recipe, or data bag was.  I know now, this was the <em>wrong</em> way to learn chef.  chef with chef-client/server adds a level of complexity that just is unfounded.  I decided to spend a copy hours to master chef-solo, and damn I wish I had started there.</p>

<h2>My hands on learning project</h2>

<p>I had a requirement of setting up a unicorn nginx instance on a VPS.  I thought hell, there&rsquo;s gotta be a way to do this with chef. (I normally use passenger+apache, so I had to learn nginx and unicorn too, but that&rsquo;s a different post&hellip;well kinda) So I looked around for a nice <a href="http://www.opinionatedprogrammer.com/2011/06/chef-solo-tutorial-managing-a-single-server-with-chef/">tutorial</a> and came across that guy.  I started reading it, realized holy crap, this is awesome.  I stole the <code>solo.json</code> and the <code>solo.rb</code> and <code>install.sh</code> because I was lazy.<br/>
I changed the <code>install.sh</code> around a little bit:
```bash</p>

<h1>!/bin/bash</h1>

<h1>This run as root on the machine</h1>

<p>chef_binary=/opt/chef/embedded/lib/ruby/gems/1.9.1/gems/chef-11.6.0/bin/chef-solo</p>

<h1>are we not bootstrapped?</h1>

<p>if ! test -f &ldquo;$chef_binary&rdquo;; then
  export DEBIAN_FRONTEND=noniteractive
  apt-get update &amp;&amp;
  apt-get dist-upgrade -y &amp;&amp;
  apt-get install ruby1.9.1 ruby1.9.1-dev make curl -y &amp;&amp;
  curl -L <a href="https://www.opscode.com/chef/install.sh">https://www.opscode.com/chef/install.sh</a> | sudo bash
fi &amp;&amp;</p>

<p>chef-solo -c solo.rb -j solo.json
<code>``
As you can tell, its ubuntu focused, but basically if I want to provision a box after making a change to one of the cookbooks I just had to run</code>./install.sh`.  Interestingly, I had heard bad things about the 1.9.1 ruby binaries for ubuntu, but so far, it is a ton better than doing that compile from src. ;)</p>

<p>So, basically with those three files, running that curl in the script, and creating a <code>cookbooks/</code> directory, I had my framework to make this project happen.</p>

<p>Now I made a mistake here.  I started off with a simple &ldquo;generic&rdquo; cookbook, with a simple <code>default.rb</code> file that called a <code>packages.rb</code> file to add some pkgs I love and run on a daily basis.</p>

<p>```ruby
%w{build-essential git-core libgdbm-dev libreadline-dev libssl-dev libyaml-dev s3cmd tmux tk-dev vim wget zlib1g-dev zsh}.each do |pkg|
  package pkg do</p>

<pre><code>action [:install]
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Now to an passive onlooker there seems nothing wrong with this, and 3 weeks ago JJ would agree with you.  JJ now says, &ldquo;Stop that, start with the webserver and the deps for that instead of the convince of something easy like package management.&rdquo;  LEARN <a href="http://berkshelf.com/">berkshelf</a> and don&rsquo;t make excuses. (at this writing, 8/2/13, I still actually haven&rsquo;t learned it, the best analogy is this, dling cookbooks is like building from source, and berkshelf is like using apt-get) Anyway I digress.</p>

<p>Back to the original story.</p>

<p>I made the <code>cookbooks/</code> directory, and when to github to pull down the newest <a href="https://github.com/opscode-cookbooks/nginx">nginx</a> cookbook.  <code>git clone https://github.com/opscode-cookbooks/nginx.git</code> in the directory and then because  I hate submodules, I ran <code>rm -rf .git/</code>. I <code>cd ~/chef-solo</code> then ran <code>install.sh</code>. Crossed my fingers and no, didn&rsquo;t work. Turns out I needed a bunch of dependences (hence the berkself statement). I resolved them all, and then ran the beautiful <code>./install.sh</code>. BOOM, it worked.  I took a moment, realized what I had just done.  I created a git repo off this work, created a branch &ldquo;nginx&rdquo; and committed my changes. Now whenever I need to spin up an nginx box, all I have to do is clone my chef-solo repo and checkout nginx and run <code>install.sh</code>.</p>

<p>Dang, that&rsquo;s awesome. To get that to work with chef-server&hellip;is a ton of work.  You have to download each cookbook, upload each to the chef-server, change the role or add the recipe, then run chef-client.  This would be great if I had to do it over and over, but being I was just setting up a dev box, chef-server overhead just isn&rsquo;t worth it.</p>

<p>Now all in all, this has only been one adventure with chef-solo, but going through this academic exercise I realized the potential of this unbelievable powerful application.  From this project, and my &ldquo;generic&rdquo; cookbook, I&rsquo;ve ran with it, so now I have a boostrap cookbook with my packages, some of my dotfiles, and other tidbits.  It&rsquo;s nice, and I strongly suggest checking it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[serverspec the new best way to learn and audit your infrastructure]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/07/12/serverspec-the-new-best-way-to-learn-and-audit-your-infrastructure/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-12T15:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/07/12/serverspec-the-new-best-way-to-learn-and-audit-your-infrastructure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Listening to the <a href="http://www.opscode.com">Opscode</a> comunity pod cast, the <a href="https://twitter.com/foodfightshow">foodfight</a> show, <a href="https://twitter.com/bryanwb">bryanwb</a> suggested more love for something called <a href="http://serverspec.org">serverspec</a>.  A couple days later he wrote a <a href="https://twitter.com/bryanwb/status/340155947634794496">tweet</a> and I figured I&rsquo;d give it a shot.  I&rsquo;ve been blown away by it; and I&rsquo;m going to sell/leverage it where ever I can.</p>

<p>serverspec is basically <a href="http://rspec.info/">rspec</a> for sysadmins, from what I&rsquo;ve tested basic rspec (and some advanced rspec) assertions work like a charm. Here&rsquo;s a <a href="https://gist.github.com/byplayer/965857">cheat sheet</a> if you want.  You can write tests like ruby developers do, but leverage them for your infrastructure.  As I&rsquo;ve been learning more about TDD, I see the advantage, but to put that style in sysadmining, might seem initially crazy.</p>

<p>As a new sysadmin, you&rsquo;ve probably had an experience something like this:
You come in at a new job, you have the initial &ldquo;Hey newguy, here&rsquo;s your new network.  You have web machines, databases, app servers, caching servers, configuration management and other boxes. We have process monitoring <em>ahem</em>nagios<em>ahem</em> and yes we have configuration management where you have to leverage code reviews to get anything out to production.&rdquo; As a new guy I&rsquo;m excited this is great, but here comes the kicker.  Your new trainer continues, &ldquo;Ok, lets walk through each machine.  There are 10 web servers, 9 of them are called www1 through www8, and one called paco.&rdquo; You quickly grab a piece of paper, &ldquo;Paco?&rdquo;, &ldquo;Yes the admin before you didn&rsquo;t like standard names, he wanted to give machines &lsquo;personality&rsquo;, and we had a management change after him, so we have that one off.&rdquo;</p>

<p>This is where serverspec comes into play.  You know that list that starts to grow, learning about your app servers, your one off web machines? If you use serverspec, you can keep the pseudo-english list and be able to check against what should be on there. It  gives you a way to confirm everything is exactly what you expect.</p>

<p>serverspec only requires ruby to run, the following command will get it installed if you have ruby 1.9.x+ installed. <code>gem install serverspec</code> and ssh access to the boxes you want to check.  The example of the webserver on the main page is priceless and speaks volumes. The following is that example with a small edit from me.
``` ruby
require &lsquo;spec_helper&rsquo;</p>

<p>describe package(&lsquo;httpd&rsquo;) do
  it { should be_installed }
end</p>

<p>describe service(&lsquo;httpd&rsquo;) do
  it { should be_enabled   }
  it { should be_running   }
end</p>

<p>describe port(80) do
  it { should be_listening }
end</p>

<p>describe file(&lsquo;/etc/httpd/conf/httpd.conf&rsquo;) do
  it { should be_file }
  it { should contain &ldquo;ServerName my-server-name&rdquo; }
end
<code>``
That's it, now all you have to do is</code>rake spec` and you have a test that checks for all the basic apache web server stuff, and instead of sshing out to each machine you can make the computer do the work for you, and this is just the tip of the iceberg!</p>

<h2>nagios (or automated process monitoring) vs serverspec</h2>

<p>I understand the hesitation about <em>another</em> monitoring solution, but every sysadmin goes through this situation like this when learning a new network.  Like the story above, there should be at least one rudimentary monitoring solution, a way to  make sure machines are up and maybe processes aren&rsquo;t erring.  With the low overhead of serverspec you can leverage this in an ad-hoc way and, I&rsquo;d like to state that this isn&rsquo;t designed to take place of something like nagios, but to augment it.</p>

<p>The advantage of something like serverspec over nagios or, a polling based monitoring solution, is that there is a lag between when you deploy something and the monitoring systems reporting it.  You can run serverspec in an ad-hoc manner you&rsquo;ll get a much faster feedback loop.  I have 1034 tests on about 40 boxes, and it only takes about 2 minutes 30 seconds to run, needless to say that&rsquo;s a small price to pay for a piece of mind.  The default polling for nagios is 5 minutes, so cutting it in half that&rsquo;s already a great turn around to see the state of the machines.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also able to get serverspec working with jenkins, and run the <code>rake</code> task every 30 minutes, and if it exits on anything other than a 0, it&rsquo;ll email out the configuration or error that it finds. I&rsquo;m still experimenting with jenkins and serverspec, but so far it&rsquo;s nice to have something other than cron running this.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>serverspec is a tool/gem that I&rsquo;ll be leveraging from now on.  I&rsquo;ve been wanting to learn rspec and this gives me an avenue to use it day to day; and get a huge benefit from it.  I even bought <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/achbd/the-rspec-book">The RSpec Book: Behaviour-Driven Development with RSpec, Cucumber, and Friends</a> by The Pragmatic Programmers, so hopefully I&rsquo;ll be able to leverage it to get to the next level. Give it a shot, and when you get all your green dots come back, you&rsquo;ll know you&rsquo;ve found a winner.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ansible vs chef vs puppet]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/06/26/ansible-vs-chef-vs-puppet/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-26T13:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/06/26/ansible-vs-chef-vs-puppet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Intro</h2>

<p>First off, I&rsquo;m going to say I&rsquo;m a chef zealot, but I&rsquo;m attempting to put together an intelligent discussion of the battle that has popped up in sysadmin discussion groups now-a-days.  Secondly, I&rsquo;m only focusing on the three systems I have exposure to, ansible the least, puppet the second, and chef the most.  I could also probably throw salt, cfengine, and others in there, but that&rsquo;s superfluous, this is my discussion so I&rsquo;m going to keep it in my scope.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going focus on the pluses of each, and use the &ldquo;Overall&rdquo; section to combine them.  In my conclusion my true thoughts will come out, so if you want the tl;dr I&rsquo;d skip down there.</p>

<h2>ansible</h2>

<p>Links:
<a href="http://www.ansibleworks.com/">homepage</a>, a great <a href="https://github.com/leucos/ansible-tuto">tutorial</a></p>

<ul>
<li>Low overhead</li>
<li>python based</li>
<li>playbook based</li>
</ul>


<p>To quote Wikipedia:</p>

<blockquote><p>Ansible is an open-source software platform for configuring and managing computers. It combines multi-node software deployment, ad-hoc task execution, and configuration management. It manages nodes over SSH and does not require any additional remote software to be installed on them. Modules work over JSON and standard output and can be written in any programming language. The system uses YAML to express reusable descriptions of systems.</p></blockquote>

<p>Probably the neatest thing about ansible is that it only requires ssh to work.  You do the work on a local box, and run the &ldquo;play book&rdquo; and it walks through the steps.  its designed to be something fast and quick to spin up boxes.  The disadvantage of this is that creep can happen; you can make sure the box is what you expect but you don&rsquo;t have the focused control of something like chef or puppet.  If you need just a webserver that is configured one way and is disposable then this is the way to go.  If you have to support something for long term though, it seems its out of scope of this product. I could be wrong but that&rsquo;s how I interperat it.</p>

<h2>chef</h2>

<p>Links:
<a href="http://www.opscode.com/">homepage</a>, a great <a href="https://learnchef.opscode.com/">tutorial</a></p>

<ul>
<li>gem or <a href="http://www.opscode.com/blog/2012/06/29/omnibus-chef-packaging/">omnibus</a> installer</li>
<li>server based or <a href="http://docs.opscode.com/chef_solo.html">chef-solo</a></li>
<li>cookbook or recipe based</li>
</ul>


<p>To quote Wikipedia:</p>

<blockquote><p>chef is a configuration management tool written in Ruby and Erlang. It uses a pure-Ruby, domain-specific language (DSL) for writing system configuration &ldquo;recipes&rdquo; or &ldquo;cookbooks&rdquo;. chef was written by Opscode and is released as open source under the Apache License 2.0. chef is a DevOps tool used for configuring cloud services or to streamline the task of configuring a company&rsquo;s internal servers. chef automatically sets up and tweaks the operating systems and programs that run in massive data centers.</p></blockquote>

<p>As I said in the intro, I love chef.  Hell if I could I&rsquo;d probably work for opscode.  As soon as I got my head wrapped around chef (which is chef&rsquo;s main problem), its quick and efficient, and its slick.  I&rsquo;ve only ever used chef with a chef server, never really touched chef-solo.  I also leveraged <a href="https://github.com/jkeiser/chef-zero">chef-zero</a> in my testing because I like the idea of uploading the cookbooks and pulling them down.  Having cookbooks on a centralized chef server, its a true &ldquo;system of record&rdquo; that doesn&rsquo;t rely on your laptop or workstation, if you do a <code>knife server create 'role[web]'</code> you know what you are going to get.</p>

<p>Something I would like to say though, a huge disadvantage of chef is the way cookbooks are controlled.  It requires constant babying, or plugins like <a href="https://github.com/jonlives/knife-spork">knife-spork</a> to make sure people don&rsquo;t mess with each others work.  I am lucky enough to work in an environment with only 2 others that have any real use for chef, so I am able to be a good gatekeeper.  I could only imagine the cluster with larger teams.  As of 6/26/13 I know this is a conversation topic and pain point, I&rsquo;d be interested to see how the workflow matures.</p>

<h2>puppet</h2>

<p>Links:
<a href="http://www.puppetlabs.com/">homepage</a>, a great <a href="http://docs.puppetlabs.com/puppet_core_types_cheatsheet.pdf">cheat sheet</a></p>

<ul>
<li>an official <a href="http://info.puppetlabs.com/download-learning-puppet-VM.html">learning</a> vm</li>
<li><a href="https://puppetlabs.com/puppet/puppet-open-source/">package</a> based</li>
<li>server based or local puppet-apply</li>
<li>manifest based</li>
</ul>


<p>To quote Wikipedia:</p>

<blockquote><p>puppet is a tool designed to manage the configuration of Unix-like and Microsoft Windows systems declaratively. The user describes system resources and their state, either using puppet&rsquo;s declarative language or a Ruby DSL (domain-specific language). This information is stored in files called &ldquo;puppet manifests&rdquo;. puppet discovers the system information via a utility called Facter, and compiles the puppet manifests into a system-specific catalog containing resources and resource dependency, which are applied against the target systems. Any actions taken by puppet are then reported.</p></blockquote>

<p>Something I&rsquo;ve always loved about puppet is the trifecta. You can easily create a manifest to control the package/file/service in only a few lines.  (check that cheat sheet above for an example) I was able to take over an infrastructure in an extremely short period of time with just that.  I didn&rsquo;t have that long to control every facet of the groupings but the investment to the reward was mind boggling fast.</p>

<h2>Overall</h2>

<p>Ok, now that my little tl;dr of the pluses are done, I can start my views overall.  puppet is a very &ldquo;eins, zwei, eins, zwei,&rdquo; type application.  With marrying it with something like <a href="http://www.cobblerd.org/">cobbler</a> you can in theory rack mount a machine, hit the power button and have a machine exactly how you want it to be in &ldquo;x&rdquo; about of time.  This is great for big companies that always want machines to cookie cutter. It could be that that&rsquo;s how I saw puppet being used, but comparing them to the two other config management systems; it really fits. Speaking of cobbler, yes, I do understand you can leverage cobbler with each of these tools, but as you can <a href="https://github.com/cobbler/cobbler/wiki/Using%20cobbler%20with%20a%20configuration%20management%20system">see</a> it just seems that cobbler and puppet are a match made in heaven.  chef on the other hand seems like it&rsquo;s designed for smaller companies with smaller teams.  It looks for cooperation, nay, requires cooperation, and its to its strength and its weakness.  Unlike puppet, chef doesn&rsquo;t default to an &ldquo;active&rdquo; mode (Ok, that&rsquo;s not fully true about puppet either, but the better practice is to have puppet in active mode from the get go).  puppet runs by default every 30 mins, to make sure its what you want to be, chef on the other hand is a pull based config-management that they even suggest &ldquo;putting chef-client&rdquo; in your crontab.  This originally bothered me, coming from the puppet world, but as i learned more about chef i realized that isn&rsquo;t its bread and butter.  chef is a way to spin up boxes for an elastic environment like AWS.  You have a massive blast of traffic, chef will trigger throw your machines in the load balancer, install apache or whatever, and you have what you expect, and 2-3 hours later you blow it away.  This is different than ansible because it is not &ldquo;automated&rdquo; per se. Remember the play books site in your local machine, you have interact with the provisioning, which for a startup seems like the correct path. In a startup you have to know exactly what machines are running, not only because of OPEX but because its your baby, you want focus and tweak; you <em>probably</em> don&rsquo;t have the budget to just blow away the boxes.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>So I&rsquo;ll say this because I believe this: each of these tools are for different &ldquo;size&rdquo; infrastructures.  You can argue as much as you want; saying that &ldquo;yes well you can use each in of the different sizes&rdquo;, but they were all seem to have a natural fit.  puppet for the corporate/enterprise space, chef for the the small corporate/budding-enterprise space, and ansible for the start ups.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
