<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: chef | jjasghar rants and ramblings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/categories/chef/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-04T14:52:56-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[JJ Asghar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[boxen is neat but man chef-solo was so much easier]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/boxen-is-neat-but-man-chef-solo-was-so-much-easier/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-25T00:24:28-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/boxen-is-neat-but-man-chef-solo-was-so-much-easier</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So over the 2013 holiday break I played around with <a href="http://boxen.github.com/">boxen</a>, I even wrote a couple beginner posts on it. If you want go check them out, I&rsquo;ll wait&hellip;..</p>

<p>So, yeah, you can tell I was pretty impressed with it right?</p>

<p>Well from a guy that uses <a href="http://getchef.com">chef</a> day in and day out, using it in a real life scenario it was a nightmare.</p>

<p>First off, I can understand some of the choices they made; like putting everything in <code>/opt/boxen</code>. Alas the disadvantage is that well EVERYTHING is in <code>/opt/boxen</code>. My company leverages <a href="http://brew.sh/">homebrew</a> for all our base development software, and it seems that boxen installs the binary at <code>/opt/boxen/homebrew</code>. This in turn confuses the hell out of the seasoned admin AND the new person developer trying just do a simple <code>brew install &lt;someapp&gt;</code>. No joke, I spent 2-3 hours trying to figure out why boxen said homebrew was installed but I couldn&rsquo;t simplify just use <code>brew</code>. I ended up symlinking like crazy not realizing that I hand to <code>source /opt/boxen/script/env.sh</code>.  Turns out it seems I completely missed that small note in the docs/wrapper script, saying you need to source it. <em>sigh</em></p>

<p>Along with that nasty turn, one of the selling points was my ability to <code>git clone</code> down my companies code from Github. Yeah that didn&rsquo;t work at all. I forgot how hard it was to make a damn directory with puppet, then to use the <a href="https://github.com/boxen/puppet-repository">puppet-repository</a> and have it fall on it&rsquo;s face only frustrated me even farther. Strike two boxen, strike two.</p>

<p>The final strike came pretty simply but I didn&rsquo;t realize how much of a pain it was. The <a href="https://github.com/boxen/puppet-mysql">puppet-mysql</a> runs it&rsquo;s socket file in both a completely different location and runs a completely nonstandard port to connect to it. Now to a sysadmin like myself, this seems negligible, neigh, not even negligible,  but put this in front of a Developer that has to change his <code>database.yml</code> and all hell breaks loose.   And to top that off, because the database.yml is part of the code base, if said Dev decides to push it back upstream it opens up a can of worms asking why we have to have something like the following for everyone:
```ruby
&lt;%
  socket = [</p>

<pre><code>ENV["BOXEN_MYSQL_SOCKET"],
"/var/run/mysql5/mysqld.sock",
"/tmp/mysql.sock"
</code></pre>

<p>  ].detect { |f| f &amp;&amp; File.exist?(f) }</p>

<p>  port = ENV[&ldquo;BOXEN_MYSQL_PORT&rdquo;] || &ldquo;3306&rdquo;
%></p>

<p>development: &amp;development
  adapter: mysql
  database: yourapp_development
  username: root
&lt;% if socket %>
  host: localhost
  socket: &lt;%= socket %>
&lt;% else %>
  host: 127.0.0.1
  port: &lt;%= port %>
&lt;% end %></p>

<h1>Warning: The database defined as &ldquo;test&rdquo; will be erased and</h1>

<h1>re-generated from your development database when you run &ldquo;rake&rdquo;.</h1>

<h1>Do not set this db to the same as development or production.</h1>

<p>test:
  &lt;&lt;: *development
  database: yourapp_test
```</p>

<p>Yeah that ain&rsquo;t worth it AT ALL.  Now that I&rsquo;ve got my bitching out of the way, on to the happiness that is chef.</p>

<p>I took what I learned from boxen, and took the plunge into chef-solo to fix this issue. I recalled attempting to use chef-solo on OSX when I first started and it was also complete disaster. I&rsquo;m betting I really had no idea what I was doing so that&rsquo;s probably a major factor in it. But now I feel have mastered it on &ldquo;the linuxes&rdquo;, and hell even wrote a sensu cookbook for windows, so I told myself to take the plunge.  Man, I&rsquo;m really glad I did; TL;DR: easy pezzy.</p>

<p>I started around noon after deciding that boxen was dead, and by 3pm I had a working framework with a <a href="http://bit.ly/jj_mac">wrapper script</a>, <a href="https://github.com/opscode-cookbooks/homebrew">homebrew</a>, and <a href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/08/02/adventures-with-chef-solo/">chef-solo</a>, why oh why didn&rsquo;t I do this originally.</p>

<p>(I pinged Fletcher Nichol about getting test-kitchen working with OSX, he sent me a gist on how to get it working, as of writing this I haven&rsquo;t attempted it yet, but hellz yes I&rsquo;m gonna kitchen this bitch up very very soon.)</p>

<p>I had some trouble with <a href="http://rvm.io">rvm</a>, automating the install was a bit tricky, but breaking it up into different <code>execute</code> and <code>bash</code> blocks allowed for solidarity. After that hooking up the <a href="https://github.com/opscode-cookbooks/dmg">dmg</a> cookbook and boom, I have my <a href="https://github.com/jjasghar/provision_mac">mac provisioning</a> system.</p>

<p>Take a look, I&rsquo;m honestly curious on what people think. Oh, take out the <code>repo.rb</code> though, it&rsquo;s specific to my company.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A chef error that has haunted me]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2014/01/20/a-chef-error-that-has-haunted-me/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-20T15:42:33-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2014/01/20/a-chef-error-that-has-haunted-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ok, you may have seen this before:
<code>ruby
23.987.33.854   * cookbook_file[/etc/init.d/apache2] action create
23.987.33.854 ================================================================================
23.987.33.854 Error executing action `create` on resource 'cookbook_file[/etc/init.d/apache2]'
23.987.33.854 ================================================================================
23.987.33.854
23.987.33.854
23.987.33.854 Net::HTTPServerException
23.987.33.854 ------------------------
23.987.33.854 403 "Forbidden"
23.987.33.854
23.987.33.854
</code></p>

<p>NOTE: Yes, that is a fake ip, and yes that server Exception isn&rsquo;t tied just to apache2.</p>

<p>If you have, you know my pain.  Turns out there is a <a href="https://tickets.opscode.com/browse/CHEF-4253">ticket</a> on this and also a couple <a href="http://sanketdangi.com/post/50897416859/chef-errors-and-their-solutions">blog posts</a> also.</p>

<p>The gist of this:</p>

<blockquote><p>This error is encountered when we have large chef recipes whose deployment time on clients is large than 15 minutes. In order to avoid this error, please increase “s3_url_ttl" value from 900 seconds to required time interval</p></blockquote>

<p>So the fix is:
```bash
[~] % sudo vim /etc/chef-server/chef-server.rb</p>

<h1>add this line: erchef[‘s3_url_ttl’] = 900 where 900 is something larger&hellip;maybe 1800?</h1>

<p>[~] % sudo chef-server-ctl reconfigure
```</p>

<p>Boom, you should be good now. No more damn 403s.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[running knife-openstack on a private rackspace instance]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/12/23/running-knife-openstack-on-a-private-rackspace-instance/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-23T10:36:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/12/23/running-knife-openstack-on-a-private-rackspace-instance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So congrats you got your new &ldquo;<a href="http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/private/">Private Cloud</a>&rdquo; from Rackspace. You are probably ecstatic to start building your new machines.
I know I was; but alas with all new toys sometimes you hit a couple stags. Here are a couple things I ran into on my first few days.</p>

<h3>First issue</h3>

<p>So I&rsquo;m a chef shop, as you might know by now (assuming you&rsquo;ve read any of my other posts). I&rsquo;ve used <a href="https://github.com/opscode/knife-rackspace">knife-rackspace</a> tons of times; and hell I even have a <a href="https://github.com/opscode/knife-rackspace/commits?author=jjasghar">commit bit</a>. So logically I thought I could leverage this same gem with different backend api points. Nope, I was hard core wrong.
You end up having to install <a href="https://github.com/opscode/knife-openstack">knife-openstack</a>. That in itself isn&rsquo;t bad at all&hellip;
<code>bash
[~] % gem install knife-openstack
</code>
Now you need to update your <code>knife.rb</code>
<code>bash
[~] % vim ~/.chef/knife.rb
</code>
In your handoff ticket, you probably got something that looks like this:
<code>bash
export OS_USERNAME=Im_awesome_admin
export OS_PASSWORD=$omeCr@zyA$$passwD
export OS_TENANT_NAME=MyCompanyName
export OS_AUTH_URL=http://10.219.0.254:5000/v2.0/
export OS_AUTH_STRATEGY=keystone:
</code>
Go ahead and copy them out to what they need to be, something like&hellip;
```ruby
knife[:openstack_username] = &ldquo;Your OpenStack Dashboard username&rdquo;
knife[:openstack_password] = &ldquo;Your OpenStack Dashboard password&rdquo;</p>

<h3>Note: If you are not proxying HTTPS to the OpenStack auth port, the scheme should be HTTP</h3>

<p>knife[:openstack_auth_url] = &ldquo;<a href="http://cloud.mycompany.com:5000/v2.0/tokens">http://cloud.mycompany.com:5000/v2.0/tokens</a>&rdquo;
knife[:openstack_tenant] = &ldquo;Your OpenStack tenant name&rdquo;
knife[:openstack_ssh_key_id] = &ldquo;my sshkey id&rdquo;
<code>
Great! So run that great command `knife openstack flavor list` to see if everything works....
</code>bash
[~] % knife openstack server list
ERROR: knife encountered an unexpected error
This may be a bug in the &lsquo;openstack server list&rsquo; knife command or plugin
Please collect the output of this command with the <code>-VV</code> option before filing a bug report.
Exception: NoMethodError: undefined method `[]&lsquo; for nil:NilClass
```
Crap..</p>

<p>Ok, lets try out with <code>-VV</code></p>

<p><code>``ruby
DEBUG: openstack_username Im_awsome_admin
DEBUG: openstack_auth_url http://10.219.0.254:5000/v2.0/
DEBUG: openstack_tenant MyCompanyName
DEBUG: openstack_insecure
/Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/gems/knife-openstack-0.8.1/lib/chef/knife/openstack_flavor_list.rb:51:in</code>rescue in run': undefined method `[]&lsquo; for nil:NilClass (NoMethodError)</p>

<pre><code>from /Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/gems/knife-openstack-0.8.1/lib/chef/knife/openstack_flavor_list.rb:41:in `run'
from /Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/gems/chef-11.8.0/lib/chef/knife.rb:485:in `run_with_pretty_exceptions'
from /Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/gems/chef-11.8.0/lib/chef/knife.rb:174:in `run'
from /Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/gems/chef-11.8.0/lib/chef/application/knife.rb:133:in `run'
from /Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/gems/chef-11.8.0/bin/knife:25:in `&lt;top (required)&gt;'
from /Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/bin/knife:23:in `load'
from /Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/bin/knife:23:in `&lt;main&gt;'
from /Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/bin/ruby_executable_hooks:15:in `eval'
from /Users/jasghar/.rvm/gems/ruby-2.0.0-p195/bin/ruby_executable_hooks:15:in `&lt;main&gt;'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Well that&rsquo;s not a lot of help eh? Turns out, if you look at the ticket that Rackspace gives you and what the <code>[:openstack_auth_url]</code> requires you&rsquo;ll see that there&rsquo;s a <code>/tokens</code> at the end. Do'h!</p>

<h3>Second issue</h3>

<p>Ok, so you got the ability to talk to your backend? Yay! But alas, you run your create&hellip;
```bash
[~] % knife openstack server create -S jj-mba-key -I 349168d3-5381-4324-8636-398d012f852b -f 1 -N testbox
Instance Name: testbox
Instance ID: 5e0ec79c-e06a-4fdb-9887-2b30ae1e5f80</p>

<p>Waiting for server&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;
Flavor: 1
Image: 349168d3-5381-4324-8636-398d012f852b
SSH Keypair: jj-mba-key
ERROR: No IP address available for bootstrapping.
```
What the hell does that mean? Well I&rsquo;m not going to explain it all but it seems that by default Rackspace names the &ldquo;public&rdquo; and &ldquo;private&rdquo; networks as &ldquo;Fixed&rdquo; and &ldquo;Floating.&rdquo;
This is triggered a fog issue, where it&rsquo;s looking at the label for a network either &ldquo;public&rdquo; or &ldquo;private&rdquo; and blows up. There is a ticket in for this <a href="https://tickets.opscode.com/browse/KNIFE-231">here</a> but it looks like it&rsquo;s stalled from late summer, early fall. Lammmeeee.</p>

<p>So you are probably saying &ldquo;Why don&rsquo;t you just rename them?&rdquo; Good for you, great idea&hellip;but no, Openstack doesn&rsquo;t support that. So at this time, it looks like you&rsquo;ll have to delete them and rebuild them with the &ldquo;public&rdquo; and &ldquo;private&rdquo; names. Hopefully you&rsquo;ve noticed this at just the begining of building out your machines, otherwise you&rsquo;ll have to nuke and pave everything you&rsquo;ve done to get the new networks in.</p>

<p>Ah!, almost forgot. Before you go I should mention a quick note, notice the lowercase p in both public and private. Yes, it&rsquo;s THAT picky&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[People keep asking me how to start with chef]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/18/people-keep-asking-me-how-to-start-with-chef/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-18T10:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/18/people-keep-asking-me-how-to-start-with-chef</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So as the title says, people keep asking me &ldquo;How to start with chef?&rdquo; This an outline of what, if I could go back in time, I would do from the beginning. I completely acknowledge that chef can be extremely confusing to start with. If you really want to learn it you&rsquo;ll have to stick with it, and do it. Good god, nothing is better than running it on a vagrant box and seeing what you expect happen happen.</p>

<h2>chef-solo is your best friend (step 1)</h2>

<p>A lot of people can start here, and end here believe it or not.  chef-solo is unbelievably powerful and can full-fill 90% of all requirements for basic usage. I spent some time looking around for a good tutorial (doing all of them that I could find), and <a href="http://www.opinionatedprogrammer.com/2011/06/chef-solo-tutorial-managing-a-single-server-with-chef/">this</a> on was the best &ldquo;I have no idea what the fuck I&rsquo;m doing.&rdquo; situation.  Modern chef installs are a tad bit different than this guy, so the &ldquo;install.sh&rdquo; changes I suggest are this:
```bash</p>

<h1>!/bin/bash</h1>

<h1>This run as root on the machine</h1>

<p>chef_binary=/opt/chef/embedded/lib/ruby/gems/1.9.1/gems/chef-11.6.0/bin/chef-solo</p>

<h1>are we not bootstrapped?</h1>

<p>if ! test -f &ldquo;$chef_binary&rdquo;; then
  export DEBIAN_FRONTEND=noniteractive
  apt-get update &amp;&amp;
  apt-get dist-upgrade -y &amp;&amp;
  apt-get install ruby1.9.1 ruby1.9.1-dev make curl -y &amp;&amp;
  curl -L <a href="https://www.opscode.com/chef/install.sh">https://www.opscode.com/chef/install.sh</a> | sudo bash
fi &amp;&amp;</p>

<p>chef-solo -c solo.rb -j solo.json
<code>``
As you can see I use the omnibus installer, not the gem, and choose the ruby version you want ;), and yes if you use those lame-ass rpm-based distros,</code>apt-get` won&rsquo;t work for you.</p>

<h2>There&rsquo;s something clever here (step 2)</h2>

<p>So awesome, you walked through the suggested tutorial, you can now run your <code>install.sh</code> and get your changes in. Grats! If you think about it, hit up the <a href="http://docs.opscode.com">Opscode Docs</a> and you&rsquo;ll discover that there&rsquo;s a resource to provision every which way. As I said at the beginning this might be all you need, if it is then use it; no real need to go any farther.</p>

<p>Ah, you&rsquo;re still here. So you DO want to farther, awesome. In step two I suggested going to the docs, that&rsquo;s cool, but sometimes you need more verbose help, that&rsquo;s my second point, it&rsquo;s time to start asking questions. Your first stop is <a href="http://webchat.freenode.net/?channels=chef">#chef</a>; it&rsquo;s manned basically 24x7, and <em>normally</em> extremely helpful. Don&rsquo;t be a douche, if you have to paste something use <a href="http://gist.github.com">gist</a> or something.  After that the main Opscode <a href="http://lists.opscode.com/sympa">mailing list</a> is great. It&rsquo;s slower, but you get much more in depth questions and conversations. Finally the third sub step is speak up, ask questions the only way to learn this is to be like &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t understand it, help!&rdquo;</p>

<h2>The only book worth a damn as of 2013/10/18 (step 3)</h2>

<p>Step three of the journey is probably the one that most people jump to initially, and this is usually where the confusion starts.  There&rsquo;s a handful of books out there on chef, this <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/chef-starter/book">one</a> is the only one worth any money.  With a strong understanding of how to provision a simple box, and where to ask questions this book will be extremely straight forward and build upon those building blocks. I&rsquo;m constantly looking for another chef bible, but most nuggets of how-to things are spread all over the internet in blog form.</p>

<h2>The fun starts here (step 4)</h2>

<p>Step four you need a chef server, you need to be able to provision multiple boxes, you understand/can find out what a role or environment is, and you need different <code>run_lists</code>.Good for you.  From here you should look at the open source <a href="http://www.opscode.com/chef/install/">chef server</a> and spin it up on another box. I should say you can use the <a href="https://getchef.opscode.com/signup">hosted chef</a>, you get up to 5 nodes with it for free, which is cool, but if you want to see everything work from the ground up, open source chef server is the way to go. (NOTE: if you are doing it in AWS/<code>$cloudprovider</code> you&rsquo;ll need at least a 4 gig box, and that&rsquo;s pushing it. You&rsquo;ve been warned.) Now spin up another box, a machine that can talk to the server that you want to provision. Start playing with <code>knife</code> add a knife plug-in for you <code>$cloudprovider</code> see if you can spin up another box using the <a href="http://docs.opscode.com/knife_bootstrap.html">knife bootstrap</a>.  Start using <a href="http://community.opscode.com/cookbooks/minitest-handler">minitest-handler-cookbook</a>, <a href="https://github.com/opscode/test-kitchen">test-kitchen</a>, and even <a href="https://github.com/acrmp/chefspec">chef-spec</a> if your feeling sassy. If you&rsquo;ve made it this far, you&rsquo;ve probably been exposed to a myriad of other tools, run with them. Trust me if someone built if for chef the chance of being helpful is extremely high.</p>

<h2>D'oh why did I do it this way? (step 5)</h2>

<p>Step five is pretty straight forward. GOTO 10. With everything you now have on your tool belt, you&rsquo;ll want to go back to your original chef-solo recipes and refactor everything. You&rsquo;ll want to add your minitests for integration testing to confirm everything is what you expect and much much more, that I&rsquo;m at a loss of listing out here. The only way to get good with chef is to do it, hack at it and wait for that converge to work. You&rsquo;ll probably love test-kitchen probably by this point.</p>

<p>This has been my cycle of working with chef, it&rsquo;s hard, confusing and honestly sometimes extremely annoying; though on the other hand the community is great, it&rsquo;s constantly changing, and adding great tools to make your life easier. When you finally get that recipe that builds that box exactly how you want it, theres nothing better to know it&rsquo;s always there and you never have to think about it again.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to fix https://chef defaulting running chef client on open source chef server]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/05/how-to-fix-https-slash-slash-chef-defaulting-running-chef-client-on-open-source-chef-server/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-05T16:59:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/05/how-to-fix-https-slash-slash-chef-defaulting-running-chef-client-on-open-source-chef-server</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I went to #chef on freenode and maek helped me out.  Here’s a run down of how to fix it. Alas the gists are gone; sorry. :(</p>

<p>If you play with open source chef you might run into this.</p>

<p><code>
18:42 j^2 so i’m having trouble with chef-client
18:42 j^2 why does it default to https://chef/blahblah?
18:43 j^2 example:
18:43 j^2 https://gist.github.com/jjasghar/5873e421a7f8365194e3
18:44 j^2 any advice?
18:44 j^2 i guess i could add it to /etc/hosts, but i’d like it to use the chef_server_url is that the point of it?
18:45 maek j^2:  I just got hit with this also
18:45 maek i think becuase chef 11 is now fronted with nginx
18:45 maek its doing a rewrite
18:45 maek for the name configured in nginx
18:45 maek in this case its hostname
18:45 maek but i assume that box cant resolve chef
18:46 j^2 lame
18:46 maek j^2:  I had to end up adding a hosts entry
18:46 maek while I wait for dns
18:46 maek I think you could do
18:46 j^2 yeah that seems like the only option but it’s stuff dumb :(
18:47 maek you could reconfigure chef
18:47 maek to use its ip
18:47 maek instead of its hostname
18:47 j^2 tried the ip in chef_server_url didnt work either; wait you mean nginx?
18:48 @ssd7 maek: Re your question above. I believe you should be able to edit bookshelf[‘vip’] in your config and the run a reconfigure
18:48 maek i dont see it htought
18:48 j^2 oh!
18:48 maek default[‘chef_server’][‘bookshelf’][‘vip’] = node[‘fqdn’]
18:48 j^2 nice looking
18:48 maek yeah
18:48 maek there it is
</code></p>

<p>Or you can do this also, I believe this is how I fixed it myself.:</p>

<p><code>
18:48 maek so you can do
18:49 maek in /etc/chef-server/chef-server.rb
18:49 maek bookshelf[‘vip’] = ‘192.168.1.1’
18:50 j^2 yeah i dont thave that file. :(
18:50 maek and run chef-server-ctl reconfigure
18:50 j^2 ah cool
18:50 maek its for overrides
18:50 maek just make it
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
