<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sysadmin | jjasghar rants and ramblings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/categories/sysadmin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-17T18:27:00-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[JJ Asghar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning git realizing that I know nothing]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/12/17/learning-git-realizing-that-i-know-nothing/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-17T13:56:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/12/17/learning-git-realizing-that-i-know-nothing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So as with all modern day &ldquo;DevOps&rdquo; guys I use a SCM [<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source_Control_Management">Source Control Management</a>] system on a daily if not hourly basis.  I&rsquo;ve been attempting to learn it more and more, and I came across this video from the <a href="http://reddit.com/r/git">/r/git</a> subreddit and I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;ve ever seen a better explanation. It&rsquo;s called <em>Git for Ages 4 and Up</em>.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/1ffBJ4sVUb4 "></iframe></div></p>

<p>I strongly suggest taking the 99ish mins to watch it, it&rsquo;s a great tutorial, with great visual examples.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also stolen some aliases that he suggests!
<code>bash
alias glp="git log --graph --pretty --all"
alias gld="git log --graph --decorate --all"
</code></p>

<p>Some useful notes that this video helped clear up for me:</p>

<p>Something else that finally cleared up to me <code>origin/master</code> means a label, while <code>origin master</code> means the remote origin with the label of master on it&rsquo;s remote side. This works with <code>origin/bugfix</code> and <code>origin bugfix</code> also, it&rsquo;s just unfortunate that the master is used twice is a very similar context.</p>

<p><code>git merge master</code> merges master into the current branch you have checked out. <code>git merge origin/master</code> merges the upstream changes of master into your current branch. <code>git merge master bugfix</code> merges the master branch into bugfix explicitly.</p>

<p><code>git push --set-upstream (or -u) origin bugfix</code> sets the upstream branch on origin to bugfix, if from your local repo.</p>

<p><code>refs/head/blah</code> is a fancy way of saying <code>blah</code> is the branch.</p>

<p><code>git push origin --tags</code> to push your tags on the local repo to the origin</p>

<p>A detached HEAD isn&rsquo;t a bad thing; it just means there&rsquo;s no branch associated with it. It&rsquo;s good to check things out but you can always <code>git checkout -b &lt;branch_name&gt;</code> if needed.</p>

<p><code>git rebase -i HEAD^^</code> go back to rebase 2 commits; rebase goes bottom up, to squash up to the top one.</p>

<p><code>rebase</code> creates a <em>new</em> line of history, not REWRITES history.</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve pushed, never rebase; it&rsquo;s not worth it. :(</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hubot+Herkou+Campfire and how I spent much more time than I thought I should]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/11/27/hubot-plus-herkou-and-how-i-spent-much-more-time-than-i-thought-i-should/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-27T11:41:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/11/27/hubot-plus-herkou-and-how-i-spent-much-more-time-than-i-thought-i-should</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I recently watched <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NST3u-GjjFw">ChatOps</a> and got sold on <a href="http://hubot.github.com/">Hubot</a>.  We had him at my company for a while, but
with a migration we lost him; so I took it upon myself to learn how to use him again.  All in all getting him running inside my company was pretty straight forward, hell even getting
node to work on my local box for local development (<a href="https://gist.github.com/isaacs/579814">this gist</a> sums it up nicely) wasn&rsquo;t hard at all.  I found myself wanting my own hubot for <a href="https://github.com/github/hubot-scripts/blob/master/src/scripts/meme_captain.coffee">memes</a> generation, or just to play around with.</p>

<p>So I decided hell, lets try out the <a href="https://github.com/github/hubot/blob/master/docs/deploying/heroku.md">heroku</a> install. It was pretty straight forward, I got my repo running, got it deployed; but I ran into an error:
<code>
ERROR Campfire request error: Error: getaddrinfo ENOTFOUND
</code>
This is what the doc says&hellip;.
<code>
% heroku config:add HUBOT_CAMPFIRE_ACCOUNT=yourcampfireaccount
% heroku config:add HUBOT_CAMPFIRE_TOKEN=yourcampfiretoken
</code>
I put my <code>HUBOT_CAMPEFIRE_ACCOUNT</code> name as my hubot&rsquo;s account name with the token which seems logical&hellip;wth man?
<code>
HUBOT_CAMPFIRE_ACCOUNT=hubotsemail@myaccountname.com
</code>
I did some searching, googling, (it seems a few people had this <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=ERROR+Campfire+request+error%3A+Error%3A+getaddrinfo+ENOTFOUND&amp;oq=ERROR+Campfire+request+error%3A+Error%3A+getaddrinfo+ENOTFOUND&amp;aqs=chrome..69i57j69i59.2689j0j9&amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;espv=210&amp;es_sm=91&amp;ie=UTF-8">issue</a>, but no fixes were posted), more reading, and it something clicked with me, maybe it&rsquo;s the actual consumer account that it connects to, not the hubot account? So I tried this:
<code>
HUBOT_CAMPFIRE_ACCOUNT=myaccountname.campfirenow.com
</code>
Damn, nope.
<code>
ERROR Campfire request error: Error: getaddrinfo ENOTFOUND
</code>
I figured I&rsquo;d try with <code>https://</code>&hellip;..
<code>
HUBOT_CAMPFIRE_ACCOUNT=https://myaccountname.campfirenow.com
</code>
Damnit.
<code>
ERROR Campfire request error: Error: getaddrinfo ENOTFOUND
</code>
Finally I started searching around actual hubot <a href="https://github.com/github/hubot/issues/329">issues</a> and came across that guy. The <code>HUBOT_CAMPFIRE_ACCOUNT</code> just needed to be the subdomain. Do'h!
<code>
HUBOT_CAMPFIRE_ACCOUNT=myaccountname
</code>
Boom, it worked.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[hub workflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/31/hub-workflow/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-31T11:01:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/31/hub-workflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently discovered <a href="https://github.com/github/hub">hub</a> and man this is really really cool. I&rsquo;m starting to fork out projects and making PRs, but it seems that when I attempt to use <code>hub pull-request</code> I get this error:
<code>bash
[~/repo/learning_git/fakedir1] % hub pull-request
Error creating pull request: Unprocessable Entity (HTTP 422)
Missing field: "head_sha"
Missing field: "base_sha"
No commits between jjasghar:master and jjasghar:blah
</code>
WTF man? What the hell does this mean? It seems I wasn&rsquo;t the only one that had this <a href="https://github.com/github/hub/issues/189">problem</a>.  It seems that the work flow (at least in my case) was the problem. Here&rsquo;s a quick fix to be able to open up a PR off a forked branch:
<code>bash
[~/repo/learning_git/fakedir1] % git add some_file
[~/repo/learning_git/fakedir1] % git commit -m "blah"
[~/repo/learning_git/fakedir1] % git push -u origin blah
Counting objects: 7, done.
Delta compression using up to 4 threads.
Compressing objects: 100% (3/3), done.
Writing objects: 100% (4/4), 351 bytes | 0 bytes/s, done.
Total 4 (delta 2), reused 0 (delta 0)
To git@github.com:jjasghar/learning_git.git
   5224edf..88ad1af  blah -&gt; blah
Branch blah set up to track remote branch blah from origin.
[~/repo/learning_git/fakedir1] % hub pull-request
https://github.com/jjasghar/learning_git/pull/1
</code>
Pretty slick eh?</p>

<p>Bonus round you can attach your PR to an issue!
<code>bash
[~/repo/learning_git/fakedir1] % hub pull-request -i 3
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[People keep asking me how to start with chef]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/18/people-keep-asking-me-how-to-start-with-chef/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-18T10:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/18/people-keep-asking-me-how-to-start-with-chef</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So as the title says, people keep asking me &ldquo;How to start with chef?&rdquo; This an outline of what, if I could go back in time, I would do from the beginning. I completely acknowledge that chef can be extremely confusing to start with. If you really want to learn it you&rsquo;ll have to stick with it, and do it. Good god, nothing is better than running it on a vagrant box and seeing what you expect happen happen.</p>

<h2>chef-solo is your best friend (step 1)</h2>

<p>A lot of people can start here, and end here believe it or not.  chef-solo is unbelievably powerful and can full-fill 90% of all requirements for basic usage. I spent some time looking around for a good tutorial (doing all of them that I could find), and <a href="http://www.opinionatedprogrammer.com/2011/06/chef-solo-tutorial-managing-a-single-server-with-chef/">this</a> on was the best &ldquo;I have no idea what the fuck I&rsquo;m doing.&rdquo; situation.  Modern chef installs are a tad bit different than this guy, so the &ldquo;install.sh&rdquo; changes I suggest are this:
```bash</p>

<h1>!/bin/bash</h1>

<h1>This run as root on the machine</h1>

<p>chef_binary=/opt/chef/embedded/lib/ruby/gems/1.9.1/gems/chef-11.6.0/bin/chef-solo</p>

<h1>are we not bootstrapped?</h1>

<p>if ! test -f &ldquo;$chef_binary&rdquo;; then
  export DEBIAN_FRONTEND=noniteractive
  apt-get update &amp;&amp;
  apt-get dist-upgrade -y &amp;&amp;
  apt-get install ruby1.9.1 ruby1.9.1-dev make curl -y &amp;&amp;
  curl -L <a href="https://www.opscode.com/chef/install.sh">https://www.opscode.com/chef/install.sh</a> | sudo bash
fi &amp;&amp;</p>

<p>chef-solo -c solo.rb -j solo.json
<code>``
As you can see I use the omnibus installer, not the gem, and choose the ruby version you want ;), and yes if you use those lame-ass rpm-based distros,</code>apt-get` won&rsquo;t work for you.</p>

<h2>There&rsquo;s something clever here (step 2)</h2>

<p>So awesome, you walked through the suggested tutorial, you can now run your <code>install.sh</code> and get your changes in. Grats! If you think about it, hit up the <a href="http://docs.opscode.com">Opscode Docs</a> and you&rsquo;ll discover that there&rsquo;s a resource to provision every which way. As I said at the beginning this might be all you need, if it is then use it; no real need to go any farther.</p>

<p>Ah, you&rsquo;re still here. So you DO want to farther, awesome. In step two I suggested going to the docs, that&rsquo;s cool, but sometimes you need more verbose help, that&rsquo;s my second point, it&rsquo;s time to start asking questions. Your first stop is <a href="http://webchat.freenode.net/?channels=chef">#chef</a>; it&rsquo;s manned basically 24x7, and <em>normally</em> extremely helpful. Don&rsquo;t be a douche, if you have to paste something use <a href="http://gist.github.com">gist</a> or something.  After that the main Opscode <a href="http://lists.opscode.com/sympa">mailing list</a> is great. It&rsquo;s slower, but you get much more in depth questions and conversations. Finally the third sub step is speak up, ask questions the only way to learn this is to be like &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t understand it, help!&rdquo;</p>

<h2>The only book worth a damn as of 2013/10/18 (step 3)</h2>

<p>Step three of the journey is probably the one that most people jump to initially, and this is usually where the confusion starts.  There&rsquo;s a handful of books out there on chef, this <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/chef-starter/book">one</a> is the only one worth any money.  With a strong understanding of how to provision a simple box, and where to ask questions this book will be extremely straight forward and build upon those building blocks. I&rsquo;m constantly looking for another chef bible, but most nuggets of how-to things are spread all over the internet in blog form.</p>

<h2>The fun starts here (step 4)</h2>

<p>Step four you need a chef server, you need to be able to provision multiple boxes, you understand/can find out what a role or environment is, and you need different <code>run_lists</code>.Good for you.  From here you should look at the open source <a href="http://www.opscode.com/chef/install/">chef server</a> and spin it up on another box. I should say you can use the <a href="https://getchef.opscode.com/signup">hosted chef</a>, you get up to 5 nodes with it for free, which is cool, but if you want to see everything work from the ground up, open source chef server is the way to go. (NOTE: if you are doing it in AWS/<code>$cloudprovider</code> you&rsquo;ll need at least a 4 gig box, and that&rsquo;s pushing it. You&rsquo;ve been warned.) Now spin up another box, a machine that can talk to the server that you want to provision. Start playing with <code>knife</code> add a knife plug-in for you <code>$cloudprovider</code> see if you can spin up another box using the <a href="http://docs.opscode.com/knife_bootstrap.html">knife bootstrap</a>.  Start using <a href="http://community.opscode.com/cookbooks/minitest-handler">minitest-handler-cookbook</a>, <a href="https://github.com/opscode/test-kitchen">test-kitchen</a>, and even <a href="https://github.com/acrmp/chefspec">chef-spec</a> if your feeling sassy. If you&rsquo;ve made it this far, you&rsquo;ve probably been exposed to a myriad of other tools, run with them. Trust me if someone built if for chef the chance of being helpful is extremely high.</p>

<h2>D'oh why did I do it this way? (step 5)</h2>

<p>Step five is pretty straight forward. GOTO 10. With everything you now have on your tool belt, you&rsquo;ll want to go back to your original chef-solo recipes and refactor everything. You&rsquo;ll want to add your minitests for integration testing to confirm everything is what you expect and much much more, that I&rsquo;m at a loss of listing out here. The only way to get good with chef is to do it, hack at it and wait for that converge to work. You&rsquo;ll probably love test-kitchen probably by this point.</p>

<p>This has been my cycle of working with chef, it&rsquo;s hard, confusing and honestly sometimes extremely annoying; though on the other hand the community is great, it&rsquo;s constantly changing, and adding great tools to make your life easier. When you finally get that recipe that builds that box exactly how you want it, theres nothing better to know it&rsquo;s always there and you never have to think about it again.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Checking CPU WAIT via nagios]]></title>
    <link href="http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/checking-cpu-wait-via-nagios/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-16T11:11:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jjasghar.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/checking-cpu-wait-via-nagios</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So our machines swap&hellip;.swap alot. There are the  typical nagios system checks, you can have the <code>check_swap</code> call, but at my company the &lt; 20 % hits so often we needed to figure out a way to get warned about crippling proformance. We discovered that when a machine has CPU WAIT spikes, the proformance for the machine tanks, so I tried to find a check for specificly monitor the CPU WAIT.  I should mention also that most/all of the boxes we run are VMs, and waiting on IO for swap makes a sad sysadmin.</p>

<p>I took a stab at creating a check myself and the following is a simple nagios check that you can run via NRPE.  The <code>PERCENTAGE</code> line is changeable, I&rsquo;d make sure your alarm reflects your error cases. We choose 10 % because that&rsquo;s when we started seeing real prefomance issues, but as all sysadmins know any CPU WAIT is bad in general.</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>!/bin/bash</h1>

<p>stateid=
CPUWAIT=<code>top -b -n 1| grep 'wa,' | awk -F ',' {'print $5'} | cut -d . -f 1 | tr -d ' '</code>
PERCENTAGE=10</p>

<p>if [ ${CPUWAIT} -le ${PERCENTAGE} ]
 then
   echo Your CPU WAIT is under ${PERCENTAGE}%
   stateid=0
elif [ ${CPUWAIT} -ge ${PERCENTAGE} ]
 then
   echo Your CPU WAIT is at ${CPUWAIT}%, your machine aint happy
   stateid=2
 fi
exit $stateid
```</p>

<p>You are probably wondering &ldquo;There are alot of great systems checks on <a href="http://exchange.nagios.org/">Nagios Exchange</a>,&rdquo; but the site is so hard to use and useally much more than I need, like in this case.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
